<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Replyes for Alexander Monro of Bearcrofts and the answers made to the petition and information presented by him to the Commissioner his Grace, and Estates of Parliament.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B04974</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1047A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R182635</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">53981697</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 53981697</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180309</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B04974)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180309)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2825:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Replyes for Alexander Monro of Bearcrofts and the answers made to the petition and information presented by him to the Commissioner his Grace, and Estates of Parliament.</title>
                  <author>Monroe, Alexander, fl. 1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>19 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: p. 15-16 bound and filmed out of order; whole stained with slight loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Monroe, Alexander, fl. 1691.</term>
               <term>Clerks of court --  Scotland --  Early works to 18000.</term>
               <term>Courts --  Scotland --  Corrupt practices --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:180309:1"/>
            <head>REPLYES FOR ALEXANDER MONRO of <hi>Bearcrofts;</hi> To the ANSWERS made to the PETITION and INFOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MATION preſented by him to the COMMISSIOMER HIS GRACE, AND ESTATES OF PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <p>WHEREAS the Anſwerer in his Preface craves leave to repreſent the point of Fact, thereby profeſſing to clear the Parliament, how far <hi>Alexander Monro</hi>'s deſire in the foreſaid Petition was contrare to the Rules of Juſtice; and in order to which clearing ſtates the matter of Fact, ſo as thereby and in the Anſwerers intention to demonſtrate that there could be but three Clerks of Seſſion, <hi>viz.</hi> One for each Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; and that particularly in the year 1594 and 1621 Acts of Sederunt were made appointing only three principal Clerks, and that no other Clerk ſhould be joyned but of conſent of theſe Principalls for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and that the ſaid Act of Sederunt was ratified in Parliament, and that there was no Legal Title for appointing two Clerks in each Office, till <hi>Tarbat</hi> procured the ſame by a Letter from the KING ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified in Parliament <hi>Anno</hi> 1685, and upon all this Inſinuating, that the Petitioner's Right to one of the Offices of Clerkſhip in conjunction with Mr <hi>John Hay</hi> in the year 1669 was Illegal, and therefore that the thruſting of him out by an impetrate Letter from the KING was no Act of wrong, eſpecially ſeing that any collour of Right Sir <hi>Archibald Primroſe</hi> then Regiſter had by his Gift to preſent the Petitioner, was a ſurrepticiouſly inſert Clauſe into the ſaid Sir <hi>Archibald</hi> his Gift, rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive unto his naming of Deputes one or moe in each of the Offices, after
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:180309:2"/>that Sir <hi>Archibald</hi> had abſtracted the Records of the year 1621, which did bear the Act of Sederunt anent three Clerks only recorded therein; and alſo that the Petitioner became troubleſome to the LORDS in the year 1674, which occaſioned the procuring the KING'S Letter for turning him out, and conſequently, that the Petitioner cannot in Juſtice be reponned to the Office of Clerkſhip, eſpecially ſeing he accepted 7000 <hi>Merks</hi> as an adequate price modified therefore, and thereupon renunced the Office.</p>
            <p>Replyed, That the Anwerer conſidering the miſtake alſewell as the Irrevolancie of theſe points of Fact accumulate by him had good reaſon to crave leave for his adventuring by ſuch an Ingenious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texture of words to impoſe upon the World in ſtead of clearing the Parliament of the Truth, and that all the abovementioned Storie ought to derogate nothing from the ſufficiency of <hi>Alexander Monro</hi>'s Title to the Clerkſhip in point of Right, nor yet hinder him from being reſtored in Juſtice to his ſaid Office notwithſtanding of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of the 7000 <hi>Merks,</hi> and Diſcharging his Office thereupon, is clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly evident from the unanſwerable Grounds following, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1mo.</hi> That as to the pretended Act of Sederunt in the year 1621, the Anſwerer confeſſes there is no ſuch Act, and therefore he ought not to ſound thereupon, nor conſequently upon the alledged Act of Parliament relative thereto, becauſe by the principle of Law <hi>Non cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur referenti niſi conſtiterit de relato,</hi> eſpecially when the ſaid Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament is neither amongſt the Printed Acts nor in the index of the Imprinted Acts; nor can the Anſwerers alleadged Cauſe and occaſion of abſtracting of the ſaid pretended Act of Sederunt be in the leaſt reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as being a moſt unjuſt reflection on Sir <hi>Archibald Primroſe,</hi> conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the World knows that Sir <hi>Archibald</hi> at the delivery up of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſters deponed he had abſtracted none; beſides that theſe Books of Sederunt have been alwayes in the Cuſtody of the Clerks of Seſſion; but which totally takes off the ſaid Reflection, Sir <hi>Archibald</hi> had no Temptation thereto, for the whole ſix Clerks came in uniformly upon Recommendation to him, ſo that there was no uſe for any indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect method.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2do.</hi> That the pretended Act of Sederunt in <hi>anno</hi> 1594, as the ſame is printed by the Anſwerer bears, That the Clerk of the Proces ſhould
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:180309:2"/>be only preſent with the LORDS at Voting, and Reaſoning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Alſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well as Mr <hi>Alexander Gibſon</hi> Clerk his Admiſſion at that time to have been of conſent of the other two principal Clerks; yet all the World knows how far that of removing the Clerks the time of advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, alſewell as the getting the incumbent Clerks conſent to a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncts Admiſſion has gone in deſuetude, in ſo much as upon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trare now about 70 years, ſix Clerks have alwayes been in uſe to ſerve, and all of them allowed to be preſent at adviſing, and this is demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated. <hi>1mo.</hi> From the Books of Sederunt as follows, <hi>viz.</hi> That in the year 1621 the Defenders acknowledge there were ſix Clerks, and the firſt Admiſſion of any Clerk thereafter, is found to be on the 25 of <hi>July</hi> 1932, when Sir <hi>John Hamiltoun</hi> Clerk Regiſter preſented Mr <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander Gibſon</hi> and <hi>John Gibſon</hi> his Brother conjunctly and ſeverally Clerks to the Seſſion in one Office, and upon the firſt of <hi>June</hi> 1636 Sir <hi>John Hay</hi> Clerk Regiſter preſented Mr <hi>John Hay</hi> and Mr <hi>William Hay</hi> his Son conjunctly and ſeverally to one Clerkſhip, and upon the firſt of <hi>June</hi> 1649 Mr <hi>David</hi> and Mr <hi>John Hayes</hi> were preſented by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter conjunctly and ſeverly to one Clerkſhip, and in the year 1661 at the ſettlement of the Government, two Clerks were preſented to each of the three Offices, who were every one of them recommended by the KING to the Clerk Regiſter, except Mr <hi>Lawrence Scot</hi> who came in in the place of Mr <hi>James Mariland</hi> who was ſo recommended, and they and the Petitioner <hi>Alexander Monro</hi> who ſucceeded to the ſaid Mr <hi>Lawrence Scot,</hi> continued in the peaceable poſſeſſion of their Offices until the year 1676 after Arbitrary power began to exert it ſelf.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2do.</hi> That in the ſpecial caſe of <hi>Alexander Monro</hi> the Petitioner his Admiſſion there was no poſſibility that Mr <hi>John Hay</hi> the incumbent Clerk for the time, his conſent could have contribute any thing, to the ſaid <hi>Alexander</hi> his Right, the ſaid Mr <hi>John</hi> his own Right and Gift be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from Sir <hi>Archibald Primroſe</hi> in the year 1661, upon the KING'S recommendation as ſaid is, but to the half of the Office only; never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs <hi>eſto,</hi> that the ſaid Mr <hi>John</hi> his conſent would have contribute anything, <hi>Alexander Monro</hi> and Mr <hi>Lawrence Scot</hi> his Predeceſſor had the ſamen ſufficiently teſtified to them by the ſaid Mr <hi>John</hi> his Acquieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence from the 1661 year of GOD, till the 1676 without ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming during their Incumbency as indeed he could not, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:180309:3"/>the eſtabliſhed cuſtom of two Clerks in each Office at that time and long before as ſaid is, and that he had no Right to reclaime, and Mr <hi>Lawrence Scot</hi> &amp; <hi>Alexander Monro</hi> were principal Clerks as well as he.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3tio.</hi> That as <hi>Alexander Monro</hi>'s Right was founded in the eſtabliſhed cuſtom and conſuetude of the Seſſions, being ſerved by ſix Clerks as ſaid is, which is ſufficient <hi>per ſe</hi> to ſuſtain his right cuſtom in ſuch Caſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing equivalent to a Law; nevertheleſs <hi>ex ſuper abundante</hi> Sir <hi>Archibald Primroſe</hi> then Lord Regiſter, and from whom the ſaid <hi>Alexander</hi> his Right did flow, had an expreſs power in <hi>Gremio</hi> of his Patent <hi>anno</hi> 1661 to Name ſix Clerks, <hi>viz.</hi> One or more in each Office as the ſame ſhould ſeem good to him, or be profitable to the Leidges, and which Clauſe is ſo far from being ſurreptiouſly ingroſſed by Sir <hi>Archibald,</hi> as is injuriouſly ſuggeſted by the Anſwerer, that upon the contrare. <hi>1mo.</hi> The Anſwerers cannot deny, but Sir <hi>Archibald</hi>'s Patent was under the KING'S great Seal, Read, and Ratified in Parliament <hi>anno</hi> 1661. and that Sir <hi>Archibald</hi> at that time preſented ſix Clerks to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that their Gifts were Read and Ratified, and they Sworn and Admitted Clerks to the Parliament, that they were alſo Sworn and Admitted Clerks to the Seſſion, and their Gifts recorded in the Books of Sederunt; and that they were 15 or 16 years in poſſeſſion before the KINGS Letter to turn out three of them was impetrate, and which Ratification not paſſing unvoted of Courſe, but in proſecution whereof ſix Clerks being Admitted by the Parliament, and in poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſerving the Parliament it is ſufficient for eſtabliſting two Clerks in every Chamber. <hi>2do.</hi> That the ſaid Letter buir no other Cauſe for overturning the eſtabliſhment and recurring to an aboliſhed and impracticable cuſtom of reſtricting the Clerks to three, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing their Nomination by the LORDS, but allanerly His MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>JESTIES pleaſure without reſpect to the conveniency of the Leidges, which was a part of the Fundation of Sir <hi>Archibalds</hi> Patent as to the point of Naming Clerks. <hi>3tio.</hi> That when the Contrivers of the ſaid impetrate Letter their deſign was ſerved, and <hi>Alexander Monro</hi> turned out, within a ſhort ſpace thereafter the whole number of ſix Clerks was reſtored by <hi>Tarbat</hi>'s Gift in <hi>anno</hi> 1681, and by an Letter from the KING in <hi>anno</hi> 1682 in Favours of <hi>Tarbat.</hi> The tenor of the Letter expreſly relates to the power of conſtituting Deputs one or more, as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:180309:3"/>Sir <hi>Archibald Primroſe per expreſſum,</hi> had and did the ſame; nor does the ſaid Letter in Favours of <hi>Tarbat,</hi> bear any thing of the incumbent Clerks conſent as is alledged by the Anſwerers, which is a Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that the power of the naming Subſtitutes in the way and manner mentioned in Sir <hi>Archibalds</hi> Gift, is alwayes held as the True and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Standart of ſubſequent Regiſters their Patents. And <hi>4to.</hi> as a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der evidence of this the LORDS of Seſſion in <hi>November</hi> the ſaid year 1682 in the Books of Sederunt do declare, that it was neceſſary there ſhould be two Clerks for each of the three Offices, or Clerkſhips of the Seſſion in reſpect of the Multitudes of Proceſs, that the Leidges might be the better diſpatched; and becauſe that formerly there had been two Clerks in each Chamber. Likeas <hi>5to.</hi> in the year 1685 there is an Act of Parliament which in effect is declaratory of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Clerks of Seſſion, and ordains two to be in each Office or Chamber; ſo that it is admired with what confidence the Anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers could adventure upon the miſrepreſenting of the point of Fact, ſo far as to aſſert that <hi>Tarbat</hi> was the firſt that procured an legal Warrand for two Clerks to officiate in each Office, which, as the ſamen was paſt Memory of Man in uſe, and Sir <hi>Archibald Primoſe</hi> Patent aforeſaid to that purpoſe, not only ratified but put in execution by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as ſaid is, ſo it was made <hi>per expreſſum</hi> the Standart of any allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged new Right purchaſed by <hi>Tarbat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4to.</hi> As it is evident from what is aboveſaid, That <hi>Alexander Monro</hi>'s Right is unqueſtionably well founded in Law, ſo is it on the other hand moſt groundleſs and Irrelevant to pretend, <hi>That the ſaid Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der was trouble ſome to the Lords, and that thereupon they were neceſſitate to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrate the Letter for turning him out.</hi> For <hi>1mo.</hi> the ſaid <hi>Alexander</hi> his car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage towards the LORDS and all others, can be teſtified by hund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reds to have been inculpable, and were it otherwayes, the LORDS no doubt might and ought to have turned him out upon a fair Tryal by order of Law, and needed not have taken ſuch an extraordinary courſe by an impetrate Letter, without allowing him an hearing. <hi>2do.</hi> The Petitioner muſt vindicate the generality of the Lords from the charge made againſt them by the <hi>Anſwerer,</hi> in that it is notar that moſt of them were alſe much ſurprized by the KING's Letter, as the Clerks themſelves: And why ſhould the LORDS have done ſuch an Act of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:180309:4"/>Injuſtice as to turn out three Clerks for the alledged fault of one, and when the removing of that one, if guilty, by the ordinary courſe of Law had been far more honourable and ſafe for their Lordſhips.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5to.</hi> The acceptance of the 7000 <hi>Merks</hi> modified, can never debare the Petitioner from being reponned in Juſtice to his Office. Becauſe <hi>1mo.</hi> The ſame was far ſhort of the adequate worth of the Place and Office, as is evident by the great Compoſitions of 10 or 12000 pounds that are given for ſuch Places by Perſons that intend no farder Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement in their Life, and the good Eſtates ſeverals have made and daily makes. <hi>2do.</hi> That both by Texts of common Law, opinion of Doctors, and practice of our own and other Nations, (as in the ſubſequent Replyes ſhall be made appear.) A Perſon in the Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner's circumſtances the time of his taking the 7000 <hi>Merks,</hi> it is under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood under ſuch impreſſion by reaſon of the KING'S Authority, who in joyned the Tranſaction, and who was ſtill on Life, and the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner under his power that as the complyance with the <hi>Kings</hi> Injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction would have been reckoned an Act of contempt, ſo the not tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of any Money at all would have been reckoned an inſolent Aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the ſame, and tended to the Petitioner's utter loſs of all, and that therefore in ſuch Caſes and Circumſtances the Petitioner's taking the Money and renuncing the Office is far from an Homologation <hi>of the unjuſt and unequal impoſed Price,</hi> or any abſolute Acquieſcence to the LORDS determination, and is only a neceſſary and Lawful conſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his own Intereſt for ſaving ſomething rather than loſe all: Therefore Perſons in ſuch Caſes ſhould be reſtored in <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grum ex capite metus &amp; impreſſionis,</hi> notwithſtanding any ſuch acceptance or Diſcharge, all which the Petitioner did very well know the time of the Diſcharge, and ſo diſcharged becauſe in thoſe circumſtances he could not better do, and yet could not be thereby prejudged in Law or reaſon whenever Juſtice could take place.</p>
            <p>And whereas the Anſwerer after his miſtated matter of Fact, allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges by way of Preface to his Dilators, That the Preſident of the meeting of the Eſtates rejected the Petitioners Claim; And that by expreſs Order of the Commiſſioners Grace the ſame was Expunged in plain Parliament out of the Act for Fines and Forefaulturs.</p>
            <p>Replyed, That theſe pretences are of a piece with the reſt of the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:180309:4"/>Anſwerers matter of Fact; for the Preſident of the meeting of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates could not hinder any thing that the Eſtates ſand juſt. And ſo it is that the Eſtates did find it juſt in the <hi>Claim of Right,</hi> to Ordain the loſs of Offices to be Redreſſed, upon which Claim of Right and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Juſtice and Equitie of the ſame, the Petitioner founds his purſute; Likeas the Reaſon why the Commiſſioners Grace expunged all Clauſes out of the Act, but ſuch as concerned Fines and Forfaulters, was indeed becauſe his Inſtructions mentioned only Fines and Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faulters, ſo that he could not conſent to any more by way of Act of Parliament and publick Law; but His GRACE never intended to put any ſtop to the Judicative power of the Parliament, as he decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Petitioner, and His GRACE having read the Petition gave it to the <hi>Preſident</hi> of the Parliament to be remitted to the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and which accordingly is remitted and Citationes execute there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon and ſeveral dyers of Court already paſt in the Commiſſion there anent.</p>
            <p>Whereas the Anſwerer at length comes to his Dilators, and alledges <hi>1mo.</hi> That the Petition whereupon the reference to the Commiſſion of Parliament is made, was not read in Parliament. <hi>2do.</hi> That the ſubject of the Petition being the loſs of Office, cannot be conſidered by the Commiſſion becauſe the clauſe relative to that ſubject was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punged out of the general Act of Parliament as ſaid is. <hi>3tio.</hi> That all Parties having Intereſt are not called, ſuch as the LORDS of Seſſion the two late Regiſters and their Repreſentatives, from whom the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders derive their Rights to their Offices, and in courſe ought there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be called, leſt otherwayes the Defenders may be excluded from their Relief, if they propone Defences their Authors not being called. <hi>4to.</hi> That the Defenders being in poſſeſſion theſe ſeven years by paſt, by vertue of a Title and Right to the Office cannot be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved until their ſaid Right be reduced, and that there is no ground of Reduction lybelled, nor Right called for to be reduced, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that no Proces ought to be ſuſtained.</p>
            <p>Replyed to the firſt, That the Petition was read in Parliament, tho not at the inſtant when it paſt; But <hi>Eſto,</hi> it had not been read, the Objection is moſt frivolous, for it was very well known not only to the Defenders, but to all the Members of Parliament, the ſame hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:180309:5"/>been deſtribute in Print long before, and that it was needleſs to have ſpent time in reading a matter which the Parliament was not at that time to dipp into and diſcuſs, and had determined only to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit <hi>the ſamine as aforeſaid;</hi> Likeas, the generality of the References to the <hi>Commiſſion</hi> are upon Petitions in courſe, without reading where the matter is previouſly underſtood; And yet the <hi>Commiſſion</hi> never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects a Reference upon that head. To the 2d: that what is formerly adduced anent the difference of the Commiſſioner his Grace, his not admitting of Reſtoration of loft Offices by a publick Law and Act of Parliament, in a <hi>Legiſlative manner;</hi> and his allowing of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to cognoſce thereupon in a <hi>Judicative capacity,</hi> is here repeated, beſide that the Lords of the Commiſſion have already cognoſced upon caſes of loſt Offices remitted to them by the Parliament, in courſe; As particularly that of the Town Clerkſhip of <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> at the inſtance of Maſter <hi>Spruel.</hi> To the third, That the point of Law is here groſly miſtaken &amp; miſrepreſented by the Anſwerer, for the Petitioners Claim and Action is upon the Edict <hi>Quod metus cauſa;</hi> And upon theſe grounds in Law that relate to impreſſions made by perſons in Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; And that therefore this Claim and Action is competent <hi>contra quemcunque poſſeſſorem</hi> of the thing extorted, as being <hi>ex equitate pretoria,</hi> a real Action <hi>&amp; in rem ſcripta;</hi> So that the Petitioner needs no more but to get the Cauſes and Occaſions of the <hi>Vis</hi> and <hi>Metus</hi> declared by the Judge, which is ſufficient <hi>ad rem vindicandam contra quemcunque poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſorem;</hi> As is clear by the Teſtimony of all Lawyers, according to the <hi>L:</hi> 9: § 8. and the <hi>L:</hi> 14: § 3: <hi>digeſt: quod metus cauſa,</hi> whereof the words are to this purpoſe, Viz. <hi>In hae actione non queritur utrum is qui convenitur an alius metum fecit ſufficit enim hoc docere metum ſibi illatum eſſe, &amp;c.</hi> And the reaſon is rendered in the ſaid <hi>L.</hi> 9. § 8. <hi>Viz. Cum haec actio in rem ſit ſcripta nec perſonam vim facientis coerceat, ſed adverſus omnes reſtitui debet id quod means cauſa geſtum eſt, &amp;c.</hi> And the Defenders may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate their Diſtreſs to their Authors and their Repreſentatives in Order to their Relief. To the 4th: That the immediate above Reply is repeated, whereby it is evident that by the principles of Law, the Petitioners Claim and Action proceeds upon ſpecial grounds, and is ſingularly ſuſtained, upon the Purſuers proving that the Office ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled was his Right, and that he was turned out of the ſame by <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:180309:5"/>and <hi>Concuſſion;</hi> So that the Purſuer is no wayes concerned what Tittle the Defenders may have, or how long they poſſeſt the Office, for the Purſuer <hi>tanquam ſpoliatus eſt ante ominia reſtituendus,</hi> according to the principles of Law abovementioned; And therefore the whole Dilators ought to be Repelled, and Proceſs ſuſtained.</p>
            <p>Whereas the Anſwerer comes at laſt to his peremptor Defences, and ſtates the Petitioner's Claime as reſolving into two Articles, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Petitioner may be reſtored to his Office of Clerkſhip, and next that the Defenders may be decerned to pay him the Emoluments of the Office ſince he did quite the ſame. And <hi>1mo.</hi> alledges abſolvitor from the Lybel as to the bygone Emoluments, in reſpect the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders were <hi>bonae Fidei Poſſeſſores, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Replyed, That the Purſuer <hi>pro loco &amp; tempore</hi> inſiſts only for being reſtored to his Office and Place.</p>
            <p>And whereas it is alleaged againſt the Reſtoration of the Purſuer to his Office. That <hi>1mo. Eſto,</hi> that the Purſuer had a ſufficient Right and Title thereto, the ſupreme Magiſtrate might for an publick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency have ſuppreſſed the Purſuers Office and Place which was E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected for the publick good, eſpecially where the Party has gotten a reaſonable ſatisfaction, and that in this Caſe the Purſuer got ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, though his Office of conjunct Clerkſhip was eſtabliſhed by no Law; And that the Clauſe in Sir <hi>Archibald Primroſe</hi> his Gift which is the Fundation of the Purſuer's Right anent the naming more Clerks than one was ſurreptious and with expreſs condition that the ſame ſhould be found conducive to the Liedges benefit.</p>
            <p>Replyed, That the Allegeance is but a Recapitulation of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Fact above redargued, and proceeds upon groſs miſtakes. For <hi>1mo.</hi> It is certain in Law, and in the conſtitution of our Government, that private Rights cannot be prejudged, even upon conſideration of publick good otherwayes then by KING and Parliament, and upon hearing the Parties and reſounding all Damnages. <hi>2do. Eſto,</hi> That the ſupreme Magiſtrate might for publick utility, diſpoſe on private Mens Intereſts on reaſonable ſatisfaction to the Party: Yet in this caſe there was no point of <hi>Publick <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tility</hi> condeſcended upon, as the cauſe of tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning out the Purſuer; but allennerly the KING'S pleaſure as the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter bears. Likeas on the contrare the publick Utility (after the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:180309:6"/>deſign was effectuate) was found to be concerned in the re-eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of the ſix Clerks, as the Act of Sederunt made thereanent <hi>anno</hi> 1682, and the Act of Parliament ratifying the Eſtabliſhment of the Clerks by two in each Office can teſtifie. <hi>3to.</hi> The acknowledgment modified to the Purſuer being but 7000 <hi>Merks,</hi> was vaſtly under the worth of his Office as aforeſaid. <hi>4to.</hi> From what is above repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it is evident, That the Purſuers Right to his Office, is unanſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably founded in Law, both upon the account of the immemorial cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of ſix Clerks, and the poſitive Faculty in his Author Sir <hi>Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bald Primoſe</hi> his Patent, and which Patent is the very Foundation and Standart of all the Right that <hi>Tarbat</hi> or any Clerk Regiſter ſenſyne had to Name ſix Clerks, and who accordingly and conform thereto <hi>per expreſſum,</hi> have named and joyned Clerks in Offices ever ſince, as aforeſaid; So that it is admired with what confidence the Defenders can ſo nauſeouſly repeat theſe miſrepreſentations in point of Fact.</p>
            <p>Whereas it is <hi>2do.</hi> alleaged againſt reſtoring the Purſuer to his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, that the Defenders are in no worſe caſe as to the point of Right, then the Purſuer; Beſides, that the Defenders have the advantage by being in poſſeſſion, <hi>&amp; in dubio potior eſt cauſa poſſidentis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Replyed, That the Alleagance is founded on a groſs miſtake, for the Purſuer is beyond competition preferable in point of Right, which no deed extorted from him by neceſſary complyance with the Kings Letter could in Law irrecoverablie extinguiſh, ſo that as the Purſuer in point of Right was <hi>prior tempore</hi> to the Defenders he is <hi>potior jure;</hi> and their poſſeſſion can avail them nothing in reſpect of the illegal and Violent way that the Purſuer <hi>deſut poſſidere</hi> as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Whereas it is <hi>3tio:</hi> alleaged againſt the Reſtoring of the Purſuer to his Office, that the whole tract of the Affair and ſteps in the proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure of turning out the Purſuer and inſtalling the Defenders in the Office of Clerkſhip are ingroſſed in the Publick Records, as the Kings Letter to the Lords, and the Lords ſentence thereon, turning out the Purſuer, with the Defenders gift from <hi>Tarbat, &amp;c</hi> So that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders having followed the publick Faith, are in perpetual ſecutitie; by the <hi>L:</hi> 6: <hi>cod: de re judicata,</hi> where it is ſaid, that <hi>geſta quae in publica monumenta tranſlata ſunt habere debent perpetuam firmitatem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Replyed, That this Alleagiance is but a pitiful Quible, and the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:180309:6"/>meaning of the Law by the Gloſs and Commentators on that Text; Is only of Teſtimonies and Depoſitions of Parties and Witneſſes, and ſuch like being once made and performed judicially, and recorded as ſuch remain in Credite and Force; Notwithſtanding both Partie and Judge afterwards die, or would offer to retract the ſame. And it is an abſurd notion in the Defenders to think that any Tranſaction or mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in it ſelf defective, being once put in Record, ſupplies its defects, or that the Recording the Kings Letter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the Books of <hi>Sederunt,</hi> precludes the Purſuer from quarrelling the wrong done him by the ſaid Letter.</p>
            <p>Whereas it is <hi>4to.</hi> Alleadged, That the Act of Sederunt made be the Lords upon turning out the Purſuer conform to the King's Letter, being homologate by the Purſuers accepting of the 7000 <hi>Merks</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in modified, the Purſuer cannot be heared to reclaime againſt the ſamen, becauſe a Sentence tho unjuſt may be homologate by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and that no Lawyer that ever underſtood but the common prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, could adviſe the Purſuer that his taking the 700 <hi>Merks</hi> could not preclude him from craving to be reponed, becauſe <hi>ſtandum eſt rei judicatae niſi a ſententia appellatum fit,</hi> and that <hi>qui qualibet modo ſententiae ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieverint</hi> cannot reclaime be the L: 5. and L: 32: <hi>Digeſtorum de re judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata.</hi> and <hi>5to.</hi> That the Purſuer did not only homologate, but <hi>ex ſuper abundante</hi> he freely Renunced and Overgave from him and his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors to Mr <hi>John Hay</hi> and his Succeſſors, his Right as one of the Clerks of Seſſion, with power to him to diſpoſe upon the profites there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which as an ample dimiſſion, ought to exclude the Purſuer, albeit he had not got a Sixpence therefore; And that the Purſuer cannot pretend any thing of <hi>Concuſſion</hi> for excuſing his ſaid Acceptance of the 7000 Merks and voluntar Renunciation; eſpecially when he never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed by Bill, nor proponed a Defence againſt his Removeal.</p>
            <p>Replyed, That the Purſuers grounds in Law whereupon to eleid thoſe laſt and ſeemingly greateſt of the Defenders Arguments (and yet as empty as all the reſt) is indeed the <hi>Concuſſion, Impreſſion</hi> &amp; <hi>Irreſiſtable,</hi> awe that was upon him by the King's Letter, and which ground of <hi>Concuſſion</hi> that the Honorable Lords of the Commiſſion may perceive the nature of the ſamen from its Cauſes and Effects in Law, and how far in the Caſe in hand the Purſuer ſhould be reponed againſt his accepting of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:180309:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>the 7000 Merks, and renuncing of his Office as Acts that can operate nothing againſt him in Law, conſidering the circumſtances he was in, the Purſuer is able to demonſtrate the ſame beyond Contradiction, &amp; that not only by direct Conſequences from poſitive Texts of common Law, that he is in the Caſe of one whoſe Deeds aforeſaid are Null, as being the effects of Fear and Impreſſion, but likewayes by the opinion of all Doctors, and moſt Famous Practitioners that ever wrote upon the point of Reſtoring againſt Deeds done <hi>per impreſſionem &amp; metum,</hi> in ſo far as they adduce the Purſuers Caſe in <hi>Terminis</hi> as the great example of their Practice and Obſervation for illuſtrating the points following. viz. <hi>What infers juſt Fear? a Fear that the firmeſt of Men may be ſubject to, and a Fear by Impreſſion and Concuſſion, and how far ſuch a Fear may endure, ſo as to conſtruct the Parties ſubſequent Deeds to have been the effects and reſults of the Fear, and nowayes acts of Freedom, or that might import the Fear to have been purged and Over.</hi> Are all at length illuſtated by <hi>Tuſchus</hi> in his Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical Concluſ. Lit: M: Concluſ: 216: &amp; Seqq.</p>
            <p>And <hi>1o. Quoad</hi> the Texts of Law, it is ſaid L: 6: 9: 7. digeſt. deacqu:vel amit:haered. <hi>Eum qui metu verborum vel aliquo timore coactus fallens adierit hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditatem five liber ſit haeredem nom fieri placet ſive ſervus ſit dominu haeredem non facere. Item</hi> L: ij: Cod: de his quae vi vel metus cauſa geſt. <hi>Cavetur ſi per im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſionem quis aliquem metuens ſaltem in mediocri officio conſtitutum rei ſuae in eo loco ubi tale officium peregit venditionis titulo fecerit ceſſionem quod emptum fuit raddatur.</hi> And <hi>ita eſt</hi> that in this Caſe of the Purſuer's there was an <hi>aliquis metus</hi> and that <hi>per impreſſionem</hi> from an perſon in <hi>ſummo officio conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuto,</hi> whoſe command in His Letter could not have been diſobeyed by the Purſuer without hazard of being conſtructed a ſeditious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temner of Authority, ſo that his acquieſcence by taking the 7000 <hi>M.</hi> impoſed upon him, was not in the leaſt an Act of his voluntar E. lection but of meer neceſſity, which therefore cannot hinder the reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him to his Office. Likeas,</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2do.</hi> The great Example that is given by <hi>Baldus</hi> in his 142 <hi>conſ.</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent the grounds and occaſions of <hi>juſt Fear</hi> is that of over Lords of Cities their injoyning the Citizens to a mutual Compromiſſion, in which Caſe <hi>Compromiſſum dicitur per metum factum eoquod teneantur parere domino.</hi> And ſicklike <hi>Anchoranus</hi> is his 299 <hi>conſ.</hi> and <hi>Fulgoſ:</hi> in his 191 <hi>conſ.</hi> upon the ſame ſubject examplifies the matter thus, <hi>That a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:180309:7"/>Perſon being ordered by the Prince to diſcharge and exoner his Debitor ſuch an Exoneration is revocable, Tanquam juſto metu facata, And that a Perſon at the Command of the Prince having accepted the Prince's Precept and Order for making payment of an undue Debt,</hi> and accordingly thereafter making <hi>Spontaneus</hi> payment; the ſaid payment is nevertheleſs Revockable <hi>mortuo Tira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nico principe tanquam metu facta.</hi> And the ſame <hi>Anchoranus</hi> in his 159 <hi>conſ. num:</hi> 4: holds it as a principle, <hi>quo confeſſio vel actus factus ex volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate in caſu in quo praecedebat juſſus &amp; coactio, non dicatur ex voluntate ſed ex neceſſitate, quia ſufficit in principe jubente nocendi potentia.</hi> And ſo it is, that in this caſe the Kings Letter preremptorly injoyned the Purſuers ſubmiſſion to the Lords determination; And which injunction being previous to his Acceptance of the ſumm determined; And the King that did ſo injoyne, being ſtill on Life, and jealous enough of the Contemners of his Commands; The Purſuers Acceptance of the ſum modified could be no Act of voluntar Acquieſcence, but the effect of his <hi>Majeſties awful recommendation and order,</hi> againſt which he ought to be reponed: And</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3tio.</hi> The inſtance that is given by <hi>Geminus</hi> in his 15 <hi>conſ: num:</hi> 10 &amp; 11: and <hi>Angelus</hi> his 378 and 379 <hi>conſ. per tot:</hi> as the moſt pregnant ground of Terror to the moſt conſtant Spirited Man, is <hi>ſolum verbale imperium Regis quod cauſet juſtum metum quando Rex conſuevit male tractare non obedientes;</hi> And <hi>ita eſt,</hi> that in this caſe the Kings poſitive Letter, is more nor a verbal Mandate, and the ſeverities that the Purſuer might have mett with, had he not obeyed the ſame, but had endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to keep his place without regard thereto, needs not to be que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned; Likeas,</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4to. Baldus</hi> in his foreſaid 142 <hi>conſ:</hi> and <hi>Angelus</hi> in his 215 and 218 <hi>conſ:</hi> adduces the Arguments following, for inferring an impreſſion or Concuſſion, <hi>viz: Quando dominus praecepit aliquid ſubditis ut faciant; I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, Quando fit compromiſſum in judicem de re tanquam litigioſa, quae non eſt litigioſa; Item, Quando compromittens proteſtatus fuit de impreſſione; Item, Quando laudum eſt iniquum;</hi> And <hi>ita eſt,</hi> That in this caſe the Purſuer was injoyned by the Kings Letter, to ſubmit to the Lords, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding there was no contraverſie or doubt ſtated anent the matter of his Office: And upon which head the Purſuer did openly and in preſence of the Lords proteſt for a hearing. And that a Repreſentation
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:180309:8"/>might be made to his Majeſtie before furder procedure; Nevertheleſs his importunity is rejected, and he removed and debarred; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he did the next day offer and attempt to go in and take poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of his place, till by the interpoſition of Friends, that feared the Event of ſuch a courſe, he was forcibly turned back. And the <hi>laudum</hi> or <hi>modification</hi> they made being but 7000. Merks, which hath been ſince raiſed by his Office in one Year was highly unequal. Likeas, in the parallel caſe of a parties proteſting, tho but privately againſt the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, and conſtraint put upon him, to acquieſce to an unequal tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action, the Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> did upon the 9 of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1543 re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore him againſt the ſaid Tranſaction, as <hi>Papon</hi> in his Collection of Arreſts, <hi>l.</hi> 16: <hi>arti:</hi> 3: <hi>dec:</hi> 10: And [therefore <hi>à fortiori,</hi> the Purſuers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming, and Teſtification of his Diſſent, and unjuſtice that was done to him, having been made openly before the Lords, and yet all to no purpoſe, is an unanſwerable Argument of the impreſſion and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſion that induced him to accept of the 7000 <hi>Merks,</hi> rather then loſe all; And therefore in Juſtice, he ought now to be reponed. Likeas,</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5to.</hi> By all the Arguments adduced by Doctors and Practitioners, for demonſtrating the continuance and endurance of Impreſſion and Concuſſion upon a Man, it is evident that at the time of the Purſuers accepting of the 7000 m: his juſt dread of the Kings diſpleaſure and fear of utter loſs, and a farder miſchief, if he had refuſed the Money, was not over; For, <hi>1mo. Caldas</hi> in his 108<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>conſ: Natta</hi> in his 450 <hi>conſ: num:</hi> 17: Holds it as a principle, that the Impreſſion and Concuſſion endures <hi>quamdiu durat princeps &amp; paſſus metum eſt in loco ubi princeps Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranidem poteſt exercere.</hi> And the reaſon rendered by <hi>Alexander</hi> in his 144 <hi>con: num:</hi> 4. Is <hi>quia odium quando eſt irrationabile preſumitur continuare nedum in ipſo genere ſed etiam quoad alia</hi> And <hi>it a eſt,</hi> That K: <hi>Ch:</hi> was yet on life the time of accepting of the 7006 <hi>Merks</hi> that was unequally modified againſt the Purſuer's will as ſaid is, and it is not to be doubted if he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in an obſtinate not taking of the 7000 <hi>Merks,</hi> but the King at leaſt thoſe who did influence him, and impetrate the foreſaid Letter from him, might have prevailed with him to have done the Purſuer more prejudice, <hi>2do, Aretinus</hi> in his 14 <hi>conſ: num.</hi> 17 and 18. <hi>Menochius</hi> 1 <hi>conſ: num:</hi> 301. <hi>Ancheranus</hi> in his 299 and 159 <hi>conſ:</hi> and <hi>Aretinus</hi> in his 96 <hi>con: num:</hi> 27 <hi>&amp; ſequent.</hi> Hold it as an principle, That in the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:180309:10"/>Caſe of Impreſſion and Concuſſion no Deed done by the Party <hi>ex in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervallo poſt impreſſionem factam,</hi> in reference to the ſubject matter of the Concuſion can import a purgation of the Impreſſion or Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of will in the Party, ſo long as the cauſe and occaſion of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion laſts, and the reaſon is rendered, <hi>Quia actus factus ex voluntate dicitur ex neceſſitate factus quando praecedebat juſſus a potente nocendi, &amp; execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio contractus facta per eum qui paſſus eſt metum non purgat metum durante cauſa metus, quia is qui vim poſſus eſt ſi ex intervallo ratificaverit cenſetur potius id feciſſe pro ſuo intereſſe quamquod voluerit metum purgare &amp; ſic donare.</hi> As <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tol:</hi> alſo holds <hi>ad leg.</hi> 4 <hi>cod. de his quae vi,</hi> &amp;c. Where he ſtates the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of payment be him that ſold throw fear to be only <hi>quo minus perderet,</hi> and nowayes for purging or paſſing from the fear— <hi>Item quod quando alia cauſa ſubeſſe poteſt nunquam purgatur me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us quia nemo preſumitur velle jactare ſuum quod jactaret ſi exequendo contractum per impreſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem initum amitteret jus ſuum.</hi> And <hi>ita eſt,</hi> That the time of the Puſuers taking the 7000 <hi>Merks</hi> the cauſe of the Impreſſion and Concuſſion was yet extant, which did Over-awe him, and his own Intereſt did induce him to take the 7000 <hi>Merks</hi> rather than loſs all, ſo that he cannot be underſtood to have gratified his Enemies, and paſt from his Right, and therefore that he ought to be reſtored to his Office. Likeas,</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6to,</hi> It is notourly known, That as by the common Law and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of all Nations, ſo likewayes by the ſpecial practice of <hi>Scotland,</hi> Tranſactions made throw Force or Concuſſion are reſtored againſt, as in the late Caſe, at the Lady <hi>Grays</hi> inſtance againſt <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> to whom ſhe diſponed an Intereſt ſhe had in the Earl of <hi>Dundces</hi> Eſtate within the value.</p>
            <p>From all which ariſes this plaine Reply to the Defenders ſaids two laſt Arguments, <hi>viz</hi> That, <hi>1mo.</hi> The Anſwerer has laboured of grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous miſtakes in point of Law, and as to the Opinion of Lawyers and Law and Cuſtom of our own and other Nations in reference to the Effects of Impreſſion, and Forcible Awe from thoſe in Authority. And the meaning of thoſe Texts in Law adduced by the Defenders anent the Authority of a ſentence or <hi>res judicata,</hi> is when the ſame proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon Lawful Citation and hearing of Parties, which cannot be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed upon in the Purſuers caſe. <hi>2do.</hi> That as by what is aboveſaid the Purſuers accepting of the 7000 <hi>Merks</hi> can import no homologation of the King's Letter and ſentence of the Lords thereupon, ſo neither can his renuncing of the Office upon his getting the ſaid 7000 <hi>Merks</hi> be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:180309:11"/>any Ratification of the Lords their proceedings of any Abdication of the Purſuers own Right, becauſe the ſentence of the Lords forced him as well to renunce the Office, as to accept of the 7000 <hi>Merks,</hi> in reſpect that the 7000 <hi>Merks</hi> was decerned to be given him for his Office, and it is not to be imagined that <hi>Hayſtoun</hi> would have payed the 7000 <hi>M.</hi> but upon a Diſcharge relative to the Purſuer his quitting the Office for which the 7000 <hi>Merks</hi> was to be the price, and therefore as the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuers accepting of the 7000 <hi>Merks</hi> was in conſtruction of Law as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; but for preventing of his own greater loſs of all, ſo likewiſe muſt his renuncing of the Office, ſeing without a Diſcharge in theſe Terms he could never have ſaved ſo much as the 7000 <hi>Merks</hi> it ſelf.</p>
            <p>And whereas the Anſwerer adduces Arguments for evincing that there could be no Concuſſion in the Purſuers Caſe. As <hi>1mo.</hi> Becauſe that no execution could have followed againſt the Purſuer upon any Article of the Lords Interloquitor, and Act turning out the Purſuer and the other two Clerks, ſo that the Purſuers not reclaiming by Bill or otherwayes, but accepting of the 7000 <hi>Merks,</hi> and removing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from the Office were Acts of his own voluntary choice, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that there could be no Concuſſion.</p>
            <p>Replyed, That the forementioned Grounds in Law are opponed, By which the Kings very written Order, with the Lords ſentence thereupon, expreſly Debarring the Purſuer by appointing his Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>league to pay him 7000 merks; And that notwithſtanding all the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulations uſed by the Purſuer with the Lords, that he might be heard, before they proceeded to any ſuch Sentence, were too weighty grounds of Awe and Neceſſity upon him to ſtay out, when once turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out as ſaid is. And in thoſe dayes not to offer contemtuouſly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſs himſelf after ſuch an Awful Letter from the King, and Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the Lords; So that his Acceptance of the Money, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were Acts of meer neceſſity, and nothing of free Election.</p>
            <p>Whereas, It is <hi>2do:</hi> contended, That there can be do Concuſſion where the Lords of Seſſion pronouncers of the ſentence had no inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, to Concuſs, but acted by Authority of the King, in a matter that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:180309:8"/>was according to the ſtanding Laws; And that the Lords ſentence was obeyed by the Party.</p>
            <p>Replyed, That the whole Alleagiance proceeds upon affected mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes certainly, for the Lords of Seſſion were not the principal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſors, what ever Acceſſion ſome of them might have had in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it about; But the Kings Letter complyed with by the Lords, was the chief mean of Impreſſion, and Awe upon the Purſuer; And which Letter commanded a matter which took away the Purſuers property, and was downright contrary to the Law of the Nation, in reference to the number of the Clerks, in ſua far as inveterate cuſtome and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetude, the benefite of the Lieges, expreſs Conceſſions by Kings, and Ratified in Parliament, can make a Law for any thing, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when the ſix Clerkſhips in three Offices, as then eſtabliſhed, is made by an expreſs Law the very Standard and Rule of the Clerk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips now and in all time coming; So that no Obedience was ever given to that ſentence of the Lords be the Purſuer, but by Force and Awe, and for ſaving his own utter Loſs, as ſaid is.</p>
            <p>Whereas it is <hi>3tio.</hi> Alleaged that <hi>eſto,</hi> there had been a diſtinct and clear Concuſſion; And that conſequently, the Sentence of the Lords had been unjuſt; That yet it was never heard, an unjuſt ſentence did vitiat the ſubject whereon it proceeded, ſo that it could not be <hi>bona fide</hi> acquired by a ſingular Succeſſor; And therefore, that the Defenders acquiring the Office <hi>bona fide,</hi> muſt be aſſoizled from reſtoring it to the Purſuer.</p>
            <p>Replyed, That the point of Law is alſo every way miſtaken here, and ſpecially in the Caſe of Concuſſion or Deeds done throw Awe and Force, as to which the Action of Reſtitution competent to the Party laeſed is in <hi>rem ſcripta,</hi> as aforeſaid; and goes directly for recovering the thing extorted from whatſomever Poſſeſſor, ſo that the Defenders ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition tho never ſo <hi>bona fide</hi> made, cannot hinder the Purſuer from getting back his own Office. And <hi>2do.</hi> there was no formal ſentence in this Caſe proceeding upon Citation or Debate, but an Act of ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar Arbitrary violence. Whereas it is <hi>4to.</hi> alleadged, That <hi>eſto</hi> there had been Concuſſion and a Right of recovering the Office thereupon competent to the Purſuer; yet the Purſuer having reſigned and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted all in favours of Mr <hi>John Hay</hi> and his Succeſſors, he can never
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:180309:9"/>be heard now to pretend to the ſaid Right of recovering his Office.</p>
            <p>Replyed, That this Argument proceeds likewayes upon a miſtake, becauſe according to the principles in Law above adduced, The Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuers Acceptance of the 7000 <hi>Merks,</hi> and thereupon Diſcharging and Renuncing, being while the King that overawed him by His Letter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, was on Life; and the Purſuer aforeſaid within His Reach and Juriſdiction all things done by him in purſuance of that Arbitration of the Lords that was ſo <hi>Maſterfully</hi> injoyned are deeds that in conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Law, are the effects of the ſame continued <hi>awe</hi> &amp; <hi>force</hi> as aforeiaid. And the ſame as if Robbers had plundered the Purſuer of 100: lib: and offered him back ten upon his Diſcharge of the whole, in which caſe no Man can imagine that by accepting the ten pounds on theſe Terms he had either prejudged himſelf, or excuſed the Robber from Reſtitution; So that the Defenders ſay nothing, unleſs they could Alleage and Prove, that after the cauſe and Occaſions of the Force and Aw that were upon the Purſuer were over; And that he might had his Option to Retake his place, or Accept the 7000: merks, he did notwithſtanding tranſact and renounce his Right, which is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible they can Alleage.</p>
            <p>And as it is evident from the principles of Common Law, poſſitive Texts, Opinions of Doctors, and practice of our Own, and other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that the Purſuers Claim is beyond contradiction Juſt; And its moſt Reaſonable upon theſe Grounds that he ſhould be Reponed; So upon the other hand, and in point of material Equitiy, and ſuitably to the proceedings of the Government, in Order to the Redreſs of theſe manifold Wrongs that were committed in theſe Latter Reigns. The Purſuers Caſe Merits ſpecial Conſideration, as that which is not only provided For by the ſame <hi>Claim of Right,</hi> mentioning loſs of Offices, <hi>per expreſſum,</hi> in Order to a Reſtoration and Redreſs of the Perſons damnified thereby; But likewayes, Equally Juſt, and Favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able with the moſt meritorious of all thoſe provided For by the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Act anent Fines and Forefautures. In reſpect, That <hi>1mo:</hi> The generality of the Parties therein mentioned, have made Bargains by themſelves or their Friends; whereas the Purſuer in this Caſe, nor any Perſon for him, had not the leaſt acceſſion to the agreeing for, or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difying the ſaid 7000 <hi>Merks</hi> for his Place; but he reſiſted the ſame to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:180309:9"/>the utmoſt of his power, as ſaid is. <hi>2do.</hi> That by the ſaid general Ah it is provided that all compoſitions for Forefaulters and Fines thoug tranſacted by the Forefaulted Perſons, or in their Names may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And that Wives or Relicks who themſelves made Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gains for their Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rents, and diſponed the ſame for Cauſes not ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate thereto, are nevertheleſs reponed againſt theſe Bargains: And <hi>ita eſt,</hi> That the Purſuer is yet in a more favourable Caſe upon the Grounds aforeſaid, in order to the repeating and being reponed to his Office, and whom therefore the very general Act it ſelf ſeems to comprehend, by declaring that it ſhall be effectual to all the Liedges Forefaulted, Fined or otherwayes le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, and to be interpreted in their Favours in the largeſt ſenſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In reſpect of all which the Purſuer ought in Law, Juſtice, and Equity, to be Reponed to his Office and Place.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:180309:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
